<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Peter Somhorst - Blog</title><link href="https://psomhorst.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://psomhorst.github.io/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://psomhorst.github.io/</id><updated>2021-04-16T21:30:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Manim and Docker on the M1 MacBook Pro</title><link href="https://psomhorst.github.io/manim-and-docker-on-the-m1-macbook-pro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-16T21:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T21:30:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Peter Somhorst</name></author><id>tag:psomhorst.github.io,2021-04-16:/manim-and-docker-on-the-m1-macbook-pro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the recent release of &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/blog/released-docker-desktop-for-mac-apple-silicon/" target="_blank"&gt;Docker Desktop for Mac (Apple Silicon)&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I'd give it a try. 
Up to now, I've ignore Docker as a serious option for my projects.
However, since I recently failed to install &lt;a href="https://www.manim.community" target="_blank"&gt;Manim Community&lt;/a&gt; and had to resolve to virtualizing Linux to make it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the recent release of &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/blog/released-docker-desktop-for-mac-apple-silicon/" target="_blank"&gt;Docker Desktop for Mac (Apple Silicon)&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I'd give it a try. 
Up to now, I've ignore Docker as a serious option for my projects.
However, since I recently failed to install &lt;a href="https://www.manim.community" target="_blank"&gt;Manim Community&lt;/a&gt; and had to resolve to virtualizing Linux to make it run, the perfect opportunity presented itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set out and followed the instructions on the &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/manimcommunity/manim" target="_blank"&gt;Docker Hub&lt;/a&gt; page for the &lt;code&gt;manimcommunity/manim&lt;/code&gt; container.
Instructions were clear enough, and soon I had Manim running inside a Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And boy was I disappointed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manim was slow. 
And I mean, really slow. 
My M1 MacBook Pro with 16 GB of RAM is supposed to be quick. 
But Manim running in a Docker container was much slower than I had gotten used to in a Linux virtual machine (Ubuntu 20.04.2 running in Parallels Desktop 16.3.2 Technical Preview).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tested a scene I've been working on. 
On the virtualized Linux install, it took 37 seconds to build.
In the Docker container it took 10 minutes and 15 seconds. 
More than 15 times as long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially frustrating was the fact Manim seemed to hang about 70% into each partial video it created.
Writing small TeX files took mulitple seconds. 
This was not good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker warned be about this:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;WARNING: The requested image's platform (linux/amd64) does not match the detected host platform (linux/arm64/v8) and no specific platform was requested&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Apparently this Docker container was not optimized for the new processor in the M1 Macs.
I set out to find the proper container built for my Mac, but was unable to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's always fun to start dabbling in a new-to-you technology like Docker only to be confronted with a huge roadblock not even an hour in.
Luckily, I've had my challenges with installing LaTeX, Python and other things on my Macs and Linux installs before. 
I had a fighting chance to get it working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cloned the &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/manimcommunity/manim" target="_blank"&gt;Docker Hub&lt;/a&gt; repo and attempted to build it.
I was quickly presented with a selection of build errors, ranging from missing compilers to PATHs not being set right.
After some trial and error I found three changes/additions that needed to be made:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;installation of &lt;code&gt;build-essential&lt;/code&gt; was required, probably for &lt;code&gt;g++&lt;/code&gt; (GNU C compiler);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;installation of &lt;code&gt;cmake&lt;/code&gt; was required to build one of the Python prerequisites that was not available for ARM processors;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the PATH needed to point to the &lt;code&gt;aarch64&lt;/code&gt; version of LaTeX in stead of the &lt;code&gt;x86_64&lt;/code&gt; version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the changes I made in &lt;a href="https://github.com/psomhorst/manim/settings" target="_blank"&gt;my fork of the repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these changes, the Docker container builds and works flawlessly, as far as I have tested it.
The speed differs a bit per project.
I get the impression that especially writing and reading files is slower, while the actual compilation of the video files is just as fast or faster than in a virtual Linux machine. 
The same project as I tested before compiles in 56 seconds in the Docker container, compared to 37 seconds in the virtual machine. 
It is a scene with a lot of TeX parts. 
The creation of the temporary .tex files is the biggest bottleneck.
Smaller projects with pure visuals are just as fast or faster in Docker as inside the virtual machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, running Manim in Docker on M1 Macs is possible and a good option for people who don't want to run a virtual machine. 
Manim seems just as performant inside a Docker container as inside a virtual machine, except for reading/writing files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to give it a try, run the command below to build the Docker container for yourself.
I would be happy to provide prebuilt containers via Dockerhub, but I've seen enough new things for today. 
If someone has an easy guide on how to provide a built for a specific architecture, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;docker build -f docker/Dockerfile github.com/psomhorst/manim&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry></feed>